the next thing we will discuss is the so
called iron law of performance for a
large part of this class we will be
looking only at the processor itself so
the processor time can be expressed as
the number of instructions per program
times the number of cycles we spend per
instruction times the clock cycle time
or the number of seconds per clock cycle
to understand why this is CPU time we
can do the following the number of
instructions per program let's say this
is the number of instructions per
program times the cycles per instruction
times number of seconds we spend per
cycle and then the cycle here we can
cross them out the instruction here we
can cross them out and we get how many
seconds per program which is the CPU
time so why do we want to think of
processor time in terms of instructions
per program cycles per instruction and
clock cycle time instead of just
measuring the overall time well because
these three components allow us to think
about different aspects of the computer
architecture and surrounding areas that
we can change so the number of
instructions per program is generally
affected by the algorithm we use and by
the compiler we use if we have a better
compiler it might result in a more
efficient program that needs fewer
instructions to do the same thing and
also our instruction set might affect
how many instructions we need to execute
in a program for example if you have
very very simple instructions it might
take more of them to execute the same
thing the number of cycles per
instruction is also affected by the
instruction set this time the simpler
instructions may take fewer cycles to do
but also our processor design can affect
how many cycles we need per instruction
we will see several techniques that
allow a processor design to spend fewer
cycles per instruction without changing
the instruction set and finally clock
cycle time is also affected by processor
design we can design a processor so that
it does very little per clock cycle the
spending less time per clock cycle and
also clock cycle time can be affected by
circuit design if we have faster
circuits they will need less time to do
the same thing that needs to be done in
the clock cycle and also by transistor
physics
because they allow us to build faster
circuits so really computer architecture
will affect the instruction set and here
we have a choice of having complex
instructions where I spend fewer of them
per program but takes more cycles to do
it or we can have simpler instructions
where we have more of them in a program
but we spend fewer cycles per
instruction and also computer
architecture is affected by processor
design so in processor design we have a
choice of making a processor that has
very short clock cycle at the expense
possibly of spending more cycles per
instruction or we can have a processor
that spends a lot of work in a cycle
thus reducing the number of cycles it
needs per instruction a good design in
terms of processor design will balance
the tool a good design in an instruction
set will balance the two